Ricardo Reyes

Q Lausanne, Switzerland

(+41) 767748020

☑ ricardo.reyes@epfl.ch

ricardo8r.github.io

R⁶ Ricardo_Reyes14

1 0000-0003-0140-9564

I am a postdoctoral researcher in model reduction and applied math. At the moment I work developing reduced basis methods for time evolving problems. I am interested in computational fluid dynamics and computational mechanics, model reduction techniques, time evolving PDEs, and digital twins applications.

Education

Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya, BarcelonaTech

Barcelona, Spain

Ph.D. IN CIVIL ENGINEERING

2014 - 2020

- Thesis: Stabilized reduced order models for low speed flows
- Advisors: Prof. Ramon Codina & Prof. Sergio Idelsohn

Universidad Nacional de Colombia

Bogota Colombia

B.Eng. in Mechanical Engineering

2005 - 2010

Research experience_

EPFL, École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Laussane, Switzerland

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER, CHAIR OF COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS AND SIMULATION SCIENCE

Feb. 2021 - Present

- Development of a reduced order modelling method for time-dependent parametric problems.
- Development of a model reduction approaches linear and nonlinear structural problems for stress and fatigue analysis.
- Implementation of the new methods in a digital twin software for large-scale wind turbine application. Joint InnoSuisse project with Akselos (https://akselos.com/).

Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya

Barcelona, Spair

DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Mar. 2014 - Mar. 2020

- Formulation of a stabilized model reduction formulation for fluid dynamics, thermodynamics and solid mechanics.
- Formulation of a hyper-reduction strategy based in adaptive mesh refinement techniques.
- Implementation of the new methods in FORTRAN code for incompressible Navier-Stokes problems, including thermally coupled and fluid-structure interaction.
- Implementation of APIs and libraries of PETSc, SLEPc, HDF5, VTK, and ParaView in a FORTRAN code for HPC applications.

Universidad Nacional de Colombia

Bogota Colomb

GRADUATE REASERCHER

Aug. 2011 - Dec. 2012

Worked as a part of the group of modeling and numerical methods (GNUM), applying fluid and solid dynamics analysis using ANSYS and OpenFOAM in the following industrial projects:

- Fatigue analysis for a truck suspension support part, estimating dynamic loads, fatigue life and fatigue security factor.
- Turbulence analysis for the inlet pipe flow of a pump to determine the relation between the vortex length and the transverse section, by computing counter flow, static pressure, turbulent kinetic energy and dissipation energy along the pipe.
- Parametric optimization of light poles made of glass fiber based on material analysis and stress reduction.

Teaching experience_

EPFL, École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Lausanne, Switzerland

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Feb. 2021 - Present

- Parallel and high-performance computing. Fall 2022
- Algèbre linéaire avancée I. Fall 2021.

Universidad Nacional de Colombia

Bogota, Colombia Aug. 2011 - Dec. 2012

TEACHING ASSISTANT

• Mathematical modelling. Spring 2012.

- Applied engineering project. Fall 2011, Fall 2012.
- Fundamentals of heat transfer. Fall 2011.

RICARDO REYES · CV



Programming FORTRAN, Python, C/C++, MPI, LaTeX, Vim, Git **Libraries & Software** HDF5, FEniCS, PETSc, SLEPc, ParaView, Matplotlib **Languages** Spanish, English, Polish (A2), French (A2)

Awards and Funding_

Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya

2020 Cum Laude. PhD dissertation

MINISTRY OF SCIENCE, TECHNOLOGY AND INNOVATION - COLOMBIA

2013-2017 PhD Fellowship, National researcher training program

Universidad Nacional de Colombia

2011-2012 Fellowship, Teaching assistant position for students with an outstanding curriculum

- Scholarship, Honors for best graduate test score
- 2008 Scholarship, Honors for best grades
- 2004 **Scholarship**, Honors for best entrance examination score

Publications

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

A posteriori error estimates in a finite element VMS-based reduced order model for the incompressible Navier-Stokes equations

Ramon Codina, Ricardo Reyes, Joan Baiges

Mechanics Research Communications. P. 103599, 2021. DOI: 10.1016/j.mechrescom.2020.103599

Element boundary terms in reduced order models for flow problems: Domain decomposition and adaptive coarse mesh hyper-reduction

Ricardo Reyes, Ramon Codina

Computer Methods in Applied Mechanics and Engineering. 368: p. 113159, 2020. DOI: 10.1016/j.cma.2020.113159

Projection-based reduced order models for flow problems: A variational multiscale approach

Ricardo Reyes, Ramon Codina

Computer Methods in Applied Mechanics and Engineering, 363; p. 112844, 2020, DOI: 10.1016/j.cma.2020.112844

Reduced order models for thermally coupled low Mach flows

Ricardo Reyes, Ramon Codina, Joan Baiges, Sergio Idelsohn

Advanced Modeling and Simulation in Engineering Sciences. 5: 28, 2018. DOI: 10.1186/s40323-018-0122-7

PRE-PRINTS AND IN PREPARATION

Reduced order modeling of parametrized pulsatile blood flows: hematocrit percentage and heart rate Catalina Farias, Camilo Bayona, Ernesto Castillo, Roberto Cabrales, Ricardo Reyes

Reduced order models for time-dependent problems using the Laplace transform Ricardo Reyes, Fernando Henriquez, Jan Hesthaven

In preparation

Reduced Order Modeling for Parametrized Generalized Newtonian Fluid Flows Ricardo Reyes, Oscar Ruz, Camilo Bayona, Ernesto Castillo, Alexis Tello Journal of computational physics, Submitted. DOI: 10.2139/ssrn.4216628

Three-Field Fluid-Structure Interaction using the Variational Multiscale Method Alexis Tello, Ricardo Reyes, Camilo Bayona, Ramon Codina In preparation